<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-09-15T20:17:05+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tanaka Mawere</title><subtitle>Incompetent C# Programmer and Keyboardist + Bassist from Harare. Currently an unfortunate medical student at UZ and pretends to exercise at times.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">On leadership and Hitler…</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/leadership/2024/09/15/on-leadership-and-hitler.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On leadership and Hitler…" /><published>2024-09-15T02:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-09-15T02:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thoughts/leadership/2024/09/15/on-leadership-and-hitler</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/leadership/2024/09/15/on-leadership-and-hitler.html"><![CDATA[<p>If you don’t know what arm-chair commentary is, this is it. Saying something just because you had thoughts while sitting on your arm chair, regardless of you thinking the thoughts through or not.</p>

<p>But that the beauty of having your own website right? I can edit this or post another one later when I have ironed out my thoughts😂.</p>

<p>I have been pondering the power of leadership; the achievements and things accomplished by a group of people are really determined by the quality of leadership that the group has. And that is obvious. We have read it so many times from books by John Maxwell, heard it so many times from YouTube motivational speakers (also known as day light scammers) and the likes…</p>

<p>But knowing something is one thing. Experiencing it is another.</p>

<h2 id="hitler-was-hitler">Hitler was ‘Hitler’</h2>

<p>My thoughts ultimately led me to Hitler. The idea of someone like Hitler actually doing what Hitler did should be absurd to literally everyone.</p>

<p>This is a man who had the most radical beliefs among a group of people but managed to convince <strong>60 million +</strong> other people of what <em>he</em> believed.</p>

<p>I’d get it if he had more “in the middle views”, but Hitler literally preached “death to the Jews” and even the people who didn’t subscribe to that, got into the act.</p>

<p><em>Sidenote: the historians among you will interject and say “He violence and murder to force people into submission” and you’d actually be proving what I am saying.</em></p>

<p>The fact that he got into that position that people were willing to lie, kill, destroy, all in the name of the Fuhrer is astonishing to say the least.</p>

<h2 id="hence">Hence…</h2>

<p>Hitler and so many other leaders you can name, these characters are proof of the power of leadership, good or bad. Whatever a group of people will achieve (once again, good or bad) lie solely on the leadership they have.</p>

<p>Whether it is committing one of the biggest ethnic cleansings in history or starting the most valuable company in the world, it’s all on the leadership!</p>

<h2 id="from-scripture">From scripture</h2>

<p>To quote scripture</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Then Jesus told them, “This very night you will all fall away on account of me, for it is written: “’I will strike the shepherd, and the sheep of the flock will be scattered.’ <em>Matthew 26 vs 31</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>We are headless chickens without a shepherd. We have no direction. And even when the shepherd is there, us as a flock are only as good as the one shepherding us.</p>

<h2 id="so">So?</h2>

<p>Back to square one I suppose.</p>

<p>I had nowhere I was going with this despite retelling the obvious.</p>

<p>Which is what I said in the introduction. When I discover where I wanted to go with this thought train, I’ll add.</p>

<p>Thanks for reading! Congratulate yourself on not having the attention span of a housefly for reading this far because of all this TikTok, dopamine nonsense.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><category term="Leadership" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hitler, Mussolini, Lenin - what do all these people have in common?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.postimg.cc/FR65nFdT/09c888b9-f4cf-46eb-b08c-e4bbfaddc429.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.postimg.cc/FR65nFdT/09c888b9-f4cf-46eb-b08c-e4bbfaddc429.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">I never understood Nelson Mandela until now…</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2024/08/05/nelson-mandela.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I never understood Nelson Mandela until now…" /><published>2024-08-05T02:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-08-05T02:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2024/08/05/nelson-mandela</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2024/08/05/nelson-mandela.html"><![CDATA[<p>I grew up watching Wiztech SABC channels like most of the people my age and I’d see Madiba being praised so much as a kid. I got it, 27 years was no joke in jail. Heck I haven’t existed for as long as this man did in jail. That’s something. More on him in a minute</p>

<p>But recently I was thinking about the concept of hope, an optimistic state of mind that tomorrow might be my day, if not, the next day.</p>

<p>I see posts on the internet that say “Zimbabweans/Africans are prayerful, why does God let this country/continent go bad as it is?” or something like that. And I was thinking that, nope. Zimbabweans aren’t prayerful just because of the number of churches. In fact, most don’t go to church because they love God.</p>

<p>I believe most Zimbabweans go to church (hence the mushrooming of pentecostal church shed everywhere) because that’s where hope is being promised.
These pastors are promising that give that and your breakthrough is near. This year is your year and other kinds of lines just so that you get your hope up.</p>

<p>Zimbabwe, as I am maturing, is a tough place for many reasons. People just wanted the country to be somewhere where your effort is rewarded. Knowing that going to work for a month will cover my food, accommodation, transport, health etc… Just the basics. But even the basics are something gotten by luck (or corruption) here hence the lack of hope.</p>

<p>Back to Mandela.</p>

<p>Being in a place designed to suck every inch of hope that you might have for just a day might be enough to break me. A month, you will definitely have killed me. What about in a year?</p>

<p>And yet Nelson Mandela, in that very place made to kill one’s hope and faith, he endured for 27 years of his life. Typing this, it hits me again and again how incredibly impressive and awe-inducing this just is and I finally get to appreciate and understand why Nelson Mandela is celebrated as Nelson Mandela.</p>

<p>I can imagine drawing a parallel to Zimbabwe, that how society, culture, politics now are in our motherland, it sometimes feels like it’s designed to kill your hope. Especially for my pals who have graduated (in medical school so 2 more years for me, hooray😣). As a kid it’s easy to have hope because the situations aren’t in your face directly, but now as you have graduated, now you <strong>have</strong> to make something of yourself (cue Winky D’s 25 right here) and you see that many of your plans aren’t working/won’t work… It’s scary</p>

<p>But there is hope. Call it youthful exuberance.</p>

<p>I want to keep this writing and I know the internet will. Probably our father’s generation wasn’t the one to restore and give us back hope in Zimbabwe but I do hope and pray that it is my generation somehow that gives hope back to Zimbabwe.
Time to really emulate Nelson Mandela and not let situations around you kill your hope.</p>

<p>Thank you for reading my writing. Tell me your thoughts.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I see a parallel between his struggles and the challenges we face in Zimbabwe, where hope can often seem elusive. Despite the systemic obstacles, I believe in the power of hope and the potential of my generation to restore it.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i0.wp.com/www.culturetype.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/mandela.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i0.wp.com/www.culturetype.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/mandela.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Run Faster by Training Slower</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/health/2024/06/11/run-faster-by-training-slower.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Run Faster by Training Slower" /><published>2024-06-11T02:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-06-11T02:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/health/2024/06/11/run-faster-by-training-slower</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/health/2024/06/11/run-faster-by-training-slower.html"><![CDATA[<p>A few years ago, I was on a morning run. That day I had told myself I am going to have an easy run, no pressure on having a fast pace. Just a nice jog to get the body started for the day.</p>

<p>As I was turning a corner into Seke road, a guy on his way to work saw me and encouraged me to up the pace. Definitely well intentioned.</p>

<p>And in that moment I thought, he’s right. Why am I even running slow? Running slow is making excuses. Up that pace. And I did so. Talk about working with peer pressure.</p>

<h2 id="how-should-i-run-actually">How should I run actually?</h2>

<p>I was proud of myself for upping the pace during that run but it conflicted me. Should I always be running at a fast pace? What exactly is the correct way to train anyway?</p>

<p>So I started reading around and I had also started studying physiology so I could get a clearer picture. Then I stumbled across the following book. <strong>80/20 Running: Run Stronger &amp; Race Faster by <em>Training Slower</em></strong>.
<img src="https://encrypted-tbn1.gstatic.com/images?q=tbn:ANd9GcQkhN3t1V_L1w11YhzOOyZjaBO5YAMZtidsYGgoku4AH3PBiRqI" alt="80/20 Running" /></p>

<p>Intuitively, we all think that for the best results, we should train hard most times. We should run fast almost every time and study hard almost every time, but 20% of what we do accounts for 80% of the results.</p>

<p>And that’s what author Matt Fitzgerald explains.</p>

<p>The core principles are the following</p>

<ul>
  <li>You should focus on running easy for most of your training, with bursts of high-intensity effort mixed in. This approach is designed to improve your fitness and fatigue resistance.</li>
  <li>Easy running strengthens the brain’s ability to resist fatigue.</li>
</ul>

<p>In a nutshell, 80% of your training should be <strong>easy and slow</strong> while only 20% should be high in intensity and should leave you wishing you had started exercising.</p>

<p>If you are running 5 days a week, 4 should be easy to mid intensity while you leave 1 day to be ballistic about your running and your training.</p>

<h2 id="8020---pareto-principle">80/20 - Pareto Principle</h2>

<p><img src="https://th.bing.com/th/id/R.0463fdba18ed9fe34ba758d3acdcc051?rik=%2b8gwnKygHSUaYw&amp;pid=ImgRaw&amp;r=0" alt="The Pareto Principle" /></p>

<p>This is what’s called the <strong>Pareto Principle</strong>. It’s not a law but it is a principle that was observed by some Italian dude way back in business but it has now been observed in so many other facets of life such as relationships and personal finance.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>20% of what we do accounts for 80% of the results.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="so-what">So what?</h2>

<p>I personally felt a pressure when I posted on my social media a run with a slower than usual pace. Fear is to hear comments such as “you are becoming slow, you slacked” but that pressure only comes from being misinformed.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>The hope is you have learnt that it’s not every day that you have to be putting in 100% of your effort into anything, or in this particular discussion, exercise. Most of your training <em>should</em> be slow, <em>should</em> be easy. But in the remaining 20%, make sure you are giving it your all.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Health" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We all think that the most results come for putting in 100% all the time, but that's just not it.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.postimg.cc/VLHDhVX6/eebb8a09-f65b-4ed1-90f5-48f1c3a6c5df.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.postimg.cc/VLHDhVX6/eebb8a09-f65b-4ed1-90f5-48f1c3a6c5df.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Praying about the Comfort Pandemic</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/faith/health/2024/05/23/praying-about-the-comfort-pandemic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Praying about the Comfort Pandemic" /><published>2024-05-23T02:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-23T02:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/faith/health/2024/05/23/praying-about-the-comfort-pandemic</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/faith/health/2024/05/23/praying-about-the-comfort-pandemic.html"><![CDATA[<p>At a recent church gathering, an elder gave us the following prayer point. “Let’s pray against the diseases that are now more prevalent in this day and age than when we were growing up: diabetes mellitus, hypertension”.</p>

<p>And as a medical student, I heard that and thought well…</p>

<p>Not because I don’t believe in prayer, but made me think of something I have long wanted to rant about.</p>

<h2 id="fat-children">Fat Children</h2>

<p>Back when I was grade 1, there was the fat kid in class. Or two. (I can talk about them because I was one of them). Hence the song “dhafu dhunda, rapedza loaf ramama.”
The song should now be “ma-dhafu dhunda…”</p>

<p>Point being the comfortable lives we have formed, the effects are clear to see in the generation of children in primary school, living the comfortable lives their parents have given them.</p>

<h2 id="and-in-adults">And in adults?</h2>

<p>The children still have a chance with their health, however the comfortable lives we have formed in adults aren’t as forgiving.</p>

<p>From the diet, there is the sedentary lives we live in which movement is at a minimum. Any form of exercise is “too painful”.
Add to that the phones that distract us and put actual healthy, neural stimulation to zero.</p>

<p>What are the results of that then?</p>

<p>Diabetes mellitus, hypertension and cancer.</p>

<p>Of course we can pray for the wisdom of knowing how to navigate our lives with these health issues
But surely we can’t pray effects of our own doing away?</p>

<h2 id="so">So…?</h2>

<p>As a medical student and as someone so passionate about health, I am particularly concerned about <strong>preventable diseases.</strong> Preventable in the sense that our daily habits and lifestyles contribute directly to the instances of diseases occurring.</p>

<p>Seeing that our lives have become so comfortable and with that, there’s no physical exercise, healthy diets or healthy brain activity, no wonder these preventable diseases are on the rise.</p>

<p>Let’s pray for wisdom but let’s act on that wisdom we get from God. Our health needs our action.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>If you haven’t gotten anything from this article, the following is the summary</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Buy stocks in pharmaceutical companies. Their stock prices are only going to get higher.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Faith" /><category term="Health" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When should we stop praying and start listening?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.postimg.cc/hjVsQ2qb/2a2a5d41-2026-40f6-8495-78f0a9f75cc5.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.postimg.cc/hjVsQ2qb/2a2a5d41-2026-40f6-8495-78f0a9f75cc5.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Shhh, let’s not talk about sin</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/faith/2024/04/02/lets-shush-about-sin-copy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shhh, let’s not talk about sin" /><published>2024-04-02T02:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-04-02T02:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/faith/2024/04/02/lets-shush-about-sin%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/faith/2024/04/02/lets-shush-about-sin-copy.html"><![CDATA[<p>Why?</p>

<p>“Because we want to keep the peace, and not hurt each other’s <em>feelings.</em> 
Besides, if you talk about sin, who are you to judge because Matthew 7 vs 1 says ‘Do not judge or you too will be judged…’ “</p>

<p>Above are the many reasons I have heard whenever I have wanted to talk about sin, whether mine or someone else’s (some of you have tensed up because you are in the ‘why talk about someone else’s sin?’ camp). I felt this article pressed upon my spirit due to the misunderstanding of the following things</p>

<ol>
  <li>Judging each other</li>
  <li>Talking about sin (and correcting)</li>
</ol>

<p>Those are two big things so let’s get right into it!</p>

<h2 id="1-judging-each-other">1. Judging each other</h2>

<h3 id="dont-judge">Don’t judge?</h3>

<p>Probably one of the most mis-used verses in the bible is Matthew 7 vs 1 which reads</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Do not judge, or you too will be judged.</p>

  <p>Matthew 7 vs 1 (NIV)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It is mishandled and taken out of context <a href="https://www.bibleref.com/Matthew/7/Matthew-7-1.html"><em>three times over</em></a>.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Christ does not say “never judge”. He warns there is a consequence to judgement.</li>
  <li>This statement is immediately followed by instructions from Christ on the proper way to use judgement.</li>
  <li>Jesus’ other teachings explicitly indicate that right judgement is necessary while hypocritical or shallow judgement is wrong. <em>Stop judging by mere appearances, but instead judge correctly.’ John 7 vs 24</em></li>
</ol>

<p>It is modern culture that has pushed this notion of we shouldn’t judge each other. Happily someone shallow (I hope they were well-meaning but unlikely) read this verse and was happy that the bible supports him/her and will be defended by it whenever someone talks about how they are sinning. “<em>Who are you to judge me?</em>”</p>

<h3 id="so-what-now">So, what now?</h3>

<p>Yeah, unfortunately, we have to judge each other <em>but in the correct way</em>. <strong>The problem has always been hypocrisy in judgement</strong>, which Jesus explicitly notes in the following verses…</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>3 “Why do you look at the speck of sawdust in your brother’s eye and pay no attention to the plank in your own eye? 4 How can you say to your brother, ‘Let me take the speck out of your eye,’ when all the time there is a plank in your own eye? 5 You hypocrite, first take the plank out of your own eye, and then you will see clearly to remove the speck from your brother’s eye.</p>

  <p>Matthew 7 vs 3 to 5 (NIV)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But notice what Jesus did (and I absolutely love it. The bible is amazing).</p>

<p>Not only did Jesus speak against hypocrisy, but He also gave the solution. Remove the plank out of your own eye, only then will you be able to <em>remove the speck from your brother’s eye.</em></p>

<p>The last part I put in italics is the part that many people forget (willingly in my opinion), that <strong>we are supposed to remove specks from each other’s eyes.</strong></p>

<p>Which is a nice segue to the second point</p>

<h2 id="2-talking-about-sin">2. Talking about sin</h2>

<p>Let’s just hammer the point home about helping each other. Paul in his first letter to the Corinthians says the following</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What business is it of mine to judge those outside the church? Are you not to judge those inside?</p>

  <p>1 Corinthians 5 vs 12 (NIV)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Let me re-write the verse.</p>

<p>“Are <em>you</em> (yes YOU) not to judge those inside?”</p>

<p>Before the “read the ‘read the verse in context’ army comes after me”, read it in context as well. Although the story is started by addressing an adulterous son, Paul is simply saying hold each other accountable when you are in the body of Christ.</p>

<p>Which is what I think is the root problem.</p>

<h3 id="we-dont-talk-about-sin-enough">We don’t talk about sin enough</h3>

<p>For reasons stated in the first paragraph, we are so scared talk about sin especially about each other’s sin (of course, if you know you have a plank in your own eye, don’t. Wait I think I have to explain this verse as well)</p>

<h4 id="sidenote---remove-the-plank-in-your-own-eye"><em>Sidenote - Remove the plank in your own eye</em></h4>

<p><em>It’s so easy to see sin in others but not our own. Be as critical of others, but be twice that to yourself. We are often kind to ourselves and give ourselves grace that we don’t give others when we judge.</em></p>

<p><em>Now, we will always sin. That’s the unfortunate part of the human condition. So does that mean we shouldn’t judge and correct each other? No. It all goes back to the heart and also, you might have a particular sin that you conquered like sexual sin, drunkenness, debauchery, lying etc. Once you have removed the planks or started the journey of removing those sins in your eye can you remove a speck from your brother and sister.</em></p>

<p><em>Back to talking about sin.</em></p>

<p>I think it’s a dis-service to have a friend that does not lovingly correct me according to the principles of our faith because they want to keep the peace. What good is it that we keep our friendship, but I lose my soul?</p>

<p>And even I know in myself, that pride might not want to listen to someone correcting me. But once that seed is planted, it will be something that will grow in me that hey, maybe I am not supposed to be doing this thing I am doing.</p>

<p>We should be able to correct and be corrected when we are wrong. That’s just how we are supposed to live in the body of Christ.</p>

<p>I see this turning a blind eye to our own and peers sin is what has made us lose our morality and made us lukewarm Christians. The standard is Christ. Remember, He instructed us to be perfect… (Matthew 5 vs 48) meaning we should imitate the loving qualities of God, who is the heavenly standard of righteousness and perfection.</p>

<p>And quite frankly, God in His love, also corrects us and does not ignore our sin, much like a parent whose child is headed in the wrong direction. Let us follow that example and help each other with sin as much as possible, in a loving and righteous manner.</p>

<p>This would be a good place to end because the last paragraph sounded like a conclusion.😂 But I have two more things on my heart to say. If you are tired, you can scroll down and respond or comment. 
Or read on. In any case, thank you for reading thus far.</p>

<h2 id="bonuses-is-this-the-plural-of-bonus">Bonus(es, is this the plural of bonus?)</h2>

<h3 id="judging-is-not-condemning">Judging is not condemning</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>‘He that is without sin among you, let him first cast a stone at her.’</p>

  <p>John 8 vs 7</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Familiar story of the woman caught in adultery. I have a friend who made the mistake of conflating ‘judging’ with ‘condemning’ and I wanted to clear this up. Yes, the Pharisees and teachers of the law had <em>judged</em> the woman (that’s how they knew she was doing wrong in the first place. I wonder what Jesus was writing down though in verse 6 and 8).</p>

<p>Their problem was that they hadn’t judged to correct or help the woman with grace, they wanted to stone her, effectively condemning her to death.</p>

<p>That’s why Jesus says “Woman, where are they? Has no one <em>condemned</em> you? “No one, sir,” she said. “Then neither do I <em>condemn</em> you,” Jesus declared. “Go now and leave your life of sin.”</p>

<p>Note the grace of Jesus that He forgives our sins and instructs us to leave our lives of sin, not condemn us to death.</p>

<h3 id="they-dont-want-help">They don’t want help</h3>

<p>So don’t. Leave them alone. Paul instructs us to distance ourselves from people living in <em>obvious sin</em> in 1 Corinthians 5. Does that mean we shouldn’t tell them about their sin? <a href="https://www.bible.com/bible/1/MAT.28.19">No. Read Matthew 28 vs 19</a></p>

<p>You run the risk of losing your own faith if you live among people who want to live in obvious sin. Do the thing Jesus said in <a href="https://www.bible.com/bible/1/MAT.10.14">Matthew 10 vs 14</a>.</p>

<p>Shake the dust off your feet and move away.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Faith" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The big, pink elephant wearing a crop-top in the room we ignore]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.postimg.cc/y8LkCRgs/e59ab246-fb33-4dc0-8ec5-7790b633d1da.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.postimg.cc/y8LkCRgs/e59ab246-fb33-4dc0-8ec5-7790b633d1da.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Starting &amp;amp; Maintaining An Exercise Habit</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/health/2024/02/19/starting-an-exercise-habit-copy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starting &amp;amp; Maintaining An Exercise Habit" /><published>2024-02-19T14:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-02-19T14:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/health/2024/02/19/starting-an-exercise-habit%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/health/2024/02/19/starting-an-exercise-habit-copy.html"><![CDATA[<p>Ever said to yourself, “Next Monday, I will start exercise?”</p>

<p>Oddly enough, you actually get round to do it on Monday and feel great after the run, gym etc.</p>

<p>Then Tuesday comes and your body is aching and you decide to rest.</p>

<p>Wednesday comes and you’d slept late the last-night so you postpone your next work out to tomorrow.</p>

<p>Thursday comes. You actually wake up on time but have zero motivation to do it.
Friday, you then conclude that maybe exercise isn’t for you.</p>

<p>Well, I have seen many people who supposedly want to start exercising who follow this exact pattern. They start good for one day, then wane off as the week progresses.</p>

<p>So I decided to write and highlight a few of the things you could do that could help start and maintain an exercise habit.</p>

<p>The disclaimer is the first point.</p>

<h1 id="1-how-much-it-means-to-you">1. How much it means to you</h1>
<p>How much does exercise, and in turn, your health mean to you? 
I said this point was a disclaimer because no matter how many hacks will follow in this article, if you do not have the intrinsic motivation to want to be healthy and exercise, they won’t work.</p>

<p>When the COVID-19 pandemic hit, I realised just how important health was. It was the healthier people who were handling the virus better. It also put into perspective that if I am not healthy, everything else won’t matter, in particular, wealth, school, career, goals etc.</p>

<p>What use is it to want wealth so as to gain freedom but are condemned to taking a tablet a day for hypertension?</p>

<p>In addition to that, exercise helps maintain my mental and emotional health, keeps my brain on its toes and increases my creativity. In other words, exercise is absolutely essential to who I am and what I value.</p>

<p>Now the question to you is how much is your health important to you?</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Side note: I see that many people also rely on the fact that they are still young hence they’ll exercise later. Truth is that the diseases that occur in old age are due to a lack of a strong, healthy foundation set now when one is young. Of course your health is going to deteriorate inevitably, but at least start deteriorating from 90% than from 60% or 50% of health.</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="2-dont-start-high">2. Don’t start high</h1>
<p>One big hurdle I see for many people is the pressure to want to run their fastest 5km everyday, lift their heaviest weight etc. Actually run themselves into the ground because that is what exercise entails.</p>

<p>False.</p>

<p>With exercise, you do more by doing less. Instead of starting out with the intention to run 5km, just get out the door and walk for a start. Walk for even 200m. Why is this important?</p>

<p>You are training your mind to just <strong>get out the door and do something</strong>, building discipline to exercise. Especially if you are starting from scratch, this is the best thing you could do for your habit training.</p>

<p>Once your mental gets used to the habit of getting out the house and doing something active, you will natural increase the workout intensity. But beware…</p>

<h1 id="3-do-8020">3. Do 80/20</h1>
<p>The world’s best athletes follow an 80/20 approach in which 80% of the time, they do light exercise. This is exercise that leaves with enough air to carry out a conversation or sing (when no one’s around of course). The other 20% is moderate to hard exercise that leaves you gasping for air.</p>

<p>An example of what this looks like is if you decide to exercise for 5 days in the week, 4 of those days are your light exercise days and only 1 day is for hard exercise.</p>

<p>This tries to shoot down the belief that people should be doing hard strenuous exercise all the time when light exercise is all that you need. What that looks like is jogging at a light, comfortable pace or walking.</p>

<h1 id="4-post-post-post">4. Post, post, post</h1>
<p>There is social pressure when posting such things. The fact that you are now aligning yourself with exercise, posting helps you maintain that habit because you have an intrinsic desire to look consistent with whatever you make public.</p>

<p>So completed a 1km run? Post it. 
Done a ten-minute workout? Post it.</p>

<p>Not wanting to disappoint the eyes of others is a strong motivator for human actions. Might as well put it to good use.</p>

<h1 id="5-discipline-over-motivation">5. Discipline Over Motivation</h1>
<p>Another thing is to know and believe that you will never be motivated to exercise except on the first day. On so many runs, during the first kilometre, I ask myself why I am doing this anyway. That’s a lack of motivation.</p>

<p>But you must be disciplined, striving to keep up an image to yourself that you are someone who does what they say they’re going to do. Point number 4 also acts as a hack for discipline.</p>

<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>
<p>These tips are by no means complete. I will keep on adding more and more, but these are what are relevant to the people I have recently interacted with.</p>

<p>I hope it helps.</p>

<p>Tell me about your exercise journey and the challenges you face and I will try to help and chime in with what I know.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Health" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Based off my recent interactions with people, here are a few pointers on how to keep an exercise habit.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.postimg.cc/Bv2XVQdS/a46e0168-8718-4a76-94c6-d96e82f36e22.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.postimg.cc/Bv2XVQdS/a46e0168-8718-4a76-94c6-d96e82f36e22.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Sign of Good Health You Don’t Know About</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/health/2024/01/29/a-sign-of-health-you-dont-know.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Sign of Good Health You Don’t Know About" /><published>2024-01-29T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-01-29T18:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/health/2024/01/29/a-sign-of-health-you-dont-know</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/health/2024/01/29/a-sign-of-health-you-dont-know.html"><![CDATA[<p>This week, we are talking about matters of the heart.</p>

<p>So in love, you should…</p>

<p>Just kidding. I know nothing about that.</p>

<p>Before reading on, please give your answer to the following and no cheating</p>

<p><strong>PS: If there’s nothing there, just wait a few seconds until the page loads</strong></p>

<script>(function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i['QP']=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){(i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)})(window,document,'script','//scripts.poll-maker.com/3012/pollembed.js','qp');</script>
<p><a href="https://www.quiz-maker.com" data-poll="5091087x675847b2-154" style="width:100%; display:block; text-align:right;">QuizWiz</a></p>

<p>So what did you choose?</p>

<p>We all know that a heart rate that is too slow, too fast or irregular can be a sign of heart disease so you can’t be blamed for choosing the first answer which is wrong.</p>

<p>And if you chose the second, more baffling answer, it’s either you know your medical physiology or you cheated somehow. I believe more of the latter.</p>

<h1 id="heart-rate-variability">Heart Rate Variability</h1>
<p>Heart Rate Variability (HRV) is a measurement of the variation in time between successive heart beats. Simple as that.</p>

<p>A high HRV, meaning the more the variation between your heartbeats has been shown to be a signal of a healthy heart. This means that instead of your heart beating at a constant rhythm of “lub dub, lub dub, lub dub, lub dub, lub dub”, you actually want your heart to do more of the following:</p>

<p>“Lub dub (pauses for a sip of tea), lub dub, lub dub, (sprints to the next beat), lub dub”.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s important to note that the variability is of fractional duration at a time. There are arrhythmias which are medical conditions in which your heart rate variability is all over the place and that’s not what I am talking about.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>HRV though, is actually a reflection of your autonomic nervous system than your heart. The autonomic nervous system is the autopilot nervous system in your body that controls a lot of vital activities you don’t control, such as breathing rate, digestion, blood pressure and of course, heart rate.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn.michaelkummer.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/Heart-Rate-Variability.jpg?strip=all&amp;lossy=1&amp;resize=770%2C347&amp;ssl=1" alt="Heart Rate Variability Image" title="Your heart doesn't beat at exact intervals and it shouldn't" /></p>

<h1 id="so-why-is-this-relevant">So why is this relevant?</h1>

<h2 id="high-hrv">High HRV</h2>

<p>Let’s start with a high HRV. 
A high HRV, according to several studies, signals a healthy heart because it reflects the heart’s ability to respond quickly to rapid changes in the body. Things that can cause it to change are environmental stimuli, emotions, mental health, stress and metabolic imbalances in the body.</p>

<p>I will extract a piece from an article from the Harvard Health blog that says it all well.</p>

<p><em>In a healthy person, HRV should increase when your heart rate drops, as it does during relaxing activities such as reading or meditating. HRV decreases as the heart rate rises, such as when you exercise or are under stress. In fact, it changes constantly, both throughout the day and from day to day.</em></p>

<h2 id="a-low-hrv">A low HRV</h2>

<p>It then follows that a low Heart Rate Variability is a sign of ill-health.</p>

<p>People with low HRV have an increased risk of Cardiovascular Disease and are less able to cope with stress. Studies have simply shown a correlation between ill-health outcomes and a low Heart Rate Variablity. Explanations as to why are still unclear.</p>

<h1 id="how-to-track-hrv">How to track HRV</h1>

<p>Unlike blood glucose levels that have a universal level that is considered good or bad, there is no one good value of what your HRV should be. It’s highly variable between people due to fitness levels, gender, diet etc.</p>

<p>What’s important to track is the trend of your HRV. If you wear a smartwatch, it probably can measure your HRV and make a trend of whether your HRV is increasing or decreasing depending on your baseline.</p>

<p>As such, it means that if someone has a higher HRV than you, it doesn’t mean they are fitter or healthier. But if you increase you HRV against a baseline that you set yourself, you know you are on the right path.</p>

<h1 id="how-to-increase-heart-rate-variability">How to increase Heart Rate Variability</h1>

<p>That’s what we all want to know now, isn’t it?</p>

<p>Well, because HRV is such an automatic process in the body, it’s not something we can directly influence or control.
Studies do show however, that people who do the following have higher levels of HRV.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Exercise regularly, especially athletes</li>
  <li>Having a healthy diet while staying hydrated</li>
  <li>Manage mental stress levels through various techniques such as sleeping on time, journalling etc</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>

<p>The take away from this article is this:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The greater your degree of physical fitness and health, the more variable the heart rate is.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A bonus marker of health in addition to HRV, is VO2 max level. This will be for another article but now you know that a constant, regular heartbeat might be a sign that you are not fit or healthy.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Health" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Should your heart rate be regular and constant when you are resting, or should it be all over the place? What's the right thing? (Might surprise you)]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.postimg.cc/qBjTz8z4/98a09f15-7d8c-4c4a-a995-94f8da258d88.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.postimg.cc/qBjTz8z4/98a09f15-7d8c-4c4a-a995-94f8da258d88.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Let There Be Light?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/health/2024/01/22/let-there-be-light.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Let There Be Light?" /><published>2024-01-22T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-01-22T18:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/health/2024/01/22/let-there-be-light</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/health/2024/01/22/let-there-be-light.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="natural-clocks">Natural Clocks</h1>
<p>Ever noticed that after using an alarm clock to wake up at a certain time, you end up not needing the alarm clock to wake up? At times, you even wake up prior to your set time all because your natural clock has adjusted to that time.</p>

<p>This natural clock in your body is found in the Suprachiasmatic Nucleus (SCN). This structure is the master clock of your body. The SCN then is what determines your <strong>Circadian Rhythm</strong> which is the natural oscillation of your body every 24 hours, running in the background to carry out essential functions and processes.</p>

<p>Your <em>Circadian Rhythm</em> is essentially then what determines the time you feel sleepy, the time you wake up and the time certain hormones are released in your body.</p>

<p>For example, <em>Growth Hormone</em> (which does exactly what’s written on the tin) is secreted while you are asleep, but little is released during the day. How the body knows when to release Growth Hormone and others in a timely fashion is dependent on the Circadian Rhythm which is function of the SCN.</p>

<p>Okay. That’s a lot of information.</p>
<h1 id="the-scn-and-awakeness">The SCN and Awakeness</h1>
<p>The single biggest thing that influences the SCN so that it carries out its Circadian pace-making activity is <strong>light</strong>, When you wake up in the morning and light hits your eyes, light influences the SCN to start waking up the body and release hormones in accordance with that.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>An example is that when light hits your eyes in the morning, cortisol which was little while you are asleep, surges up and fills up your blood stream under instruction by the SCN.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Conversely, at night, light is dimming down, and less light is getting to the SCN through your eyes. The SCN now releases hormones and inhibits some to prepare to sleep and rest for the night.</p>

<p>The way the SCN decides to do certain things during the day and night and in a timely fashion is what we call the <strong>Circadian Rhythm</strong>.</p>

<h1 id="why-does-this-all-matter">Why does this all matter?</h1>
<p>All I was saying before is an attempt to lay the groundwork for you to understand the deleterious effects of light at the wrong time of the day and the importance of waking up at the same time of day, everyday.</p>

<h2 id="in-relation-to-sleep">In relation to sleep</h2>
<p>We have created a bright future (pun intended) in which at night, we have bulbs glaring and phones on. We don’t get a rest from light especially towards sleep so that the SCN gets the signal that it should prepare the body for sleep. Light keeps the body awake, making the SCN think that it is still day.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tip: If you wake up in the middle of the night, the absolute worst thing you could do to yourself if you intend on going back to sleep is <em>use your phone.</em> From this discussion, light will make your SCN think it’s now day and wake up your body in a way that you will find it hard to go back to sleep.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Our constant exposure to light is contributing to the sleep epidemic we are facing in which high quality sleep in going downhill. People are going to bed and spend an hour awake, twisting and turning endlessly as sleep evades them.</p>

<p>That’s where the following advice comes from. Avoid looking at a screen an hour before you sleep. Or if you really need to use your phone, turn down the blue light as it is the most arousing light to the human body.</p>

<h3 id="get-enough-light-in-the-morning">Get enough light in the morning</h3>

<p>When you do intend to wake up, it’s recommended that you go outside and have natural light come into your eyes. Phone light has the same effect but is weaker in comparison.</p>

<p>Sunlight properly wakes your body up and increases your mood to face the day. Phone light on the other hand, does a “partial job”. One in which you are up but are sluggish, which explains the sluggishness of getting out of bed after using your phone in the morning.</p>

<h2 id="in-relation-to-wake-up-times">In relation to wake up times</h2>
<p>This should have been a separate article, but it seems apposite to mention this here since the discussion is on the Circadian Rhythm and the Suprachiasmatic Nucleus (SCN),</p>

<p>It’s not always possible to wake up at the same time every day. Life so happens that you sleep late the previous night, or something happens in the middle of the night i.e. visits from our relatives that pass through walls at night.</p>

<p>Despite this, it is important to keep a consistent wake up time, even on weekends. The goal of this is to keep your Circadian Rhythm, in rhythm. Your body wants to have a rhythm, having constant times that it releases certain hormones and times it stops releasing them.</p>

<p>Of importance to this is the stress hormone, Cortisol. It is an <strong>anti-inflammatory hormone</strong> that is secreted in bucket-loads according to your Circadian Rhythm when you wake up and is prevented from being secreted into your blood stream when you are asleep.</p>

<p>Cortisol stops inflammation as it says on the tin, preventing chronic diseases such as Crohn’s disease, Ulcerative Colitis, Vasculitis, Arthritis and Psoriasis.</p>

<p>As such, cortisol being in balance is important and should be a motivating factor for one to wake up at a consistent time.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The absolute time doesn’t matter that much. If you decide to wake up at 5am, 6am or 7am, that doesn’t matter. What matters is that you have gotten adequate, long enough sleep (6 to 8 hours) of high quality.</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>
<p>The takeaway message from this article is to expose yourself to sunlight in the morning, decrease your exposure to light at night as you want to sleep and to wake up consistently at the same time.</p>

<p>All these things have major consequences on your physical and mental health, improving mood, minimising inflammation and giving you high quality sleep.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Health" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this article, I dive into the links between light and our sleep and health. In addition, I highlight the importance of waking up at the same time every day.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.postimg.cc/P5J10GKQ/a3b736b6-7ff8-47f9-9c9c-6e54aaae087a.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.postimg.cc/P5J10GKQ/a3b736b6-7ff8-47f9-9c9c-6e54aaae087a.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Misconception of Fruit Juice</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/health/2024/01/15/the-misconception-of-fruit-juice.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Misconception of Fruit Juice" /><published>2024-01-15T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-01-15T18:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/health/2024/01/15/the-misconception-of-fruit-juice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/health/2024/01/15/the-misconception-of-fruit-juice.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-story">The Story</h1>

<p>I have a friend who drinks fruit juice <strong>everyday</strong>. When I say everyday, I mean every single waking day. She loves it.</p>

<p>And she has long believed that it is a healthy alternative to drinking Coke and Varun battery acids (Pepsi, Mirinda).</p>

<p>And I don’t blame her at all. 2020 when I started being interested in health and the science and data around it, I was led to believe that I can dump fizzy drinks and gouge fruit juices with no problem. A quick search on Google will easily recommend fruit juices as a healthy alternative which it is not.</p>

<h1 id="why-is-fruit-juice-bad">Why is fruit juice bad?</h1>

<p>It’s all because of the marketing.</p>

<p>Fruit juice is presented as a healthy alternative to fizzy drinks when in actuality, they both pack in the same amount of sugar. Hence it is easy for someone to believe that they are doing well by drinking fruit juice but they are doing just as much harm to themselves as drinking an equal amount of battery acid, oops, I meant to say Mirinda.</p>

<h1 id="fruit-vs-fruit-juice">Fruit vs Fruit Juice</h1>

<p>Fruits naturally have a lot of sugar in them. A lot of it.</p>

<p>But they also have a lot of fibre. Humans cannot digest fibre naturally so it forms a mesh or a net that lines the small intestines, stopping absorption of a lot of sugar from the fruit.</p>

<p>Hence fruits pack in a lot of sugar but you don’t absorb all of it because of the fibre they contain.</p>

<p>Contrast that with fruit juice which is totally devoid of fibre but packs in the sugar. That mean your body will absorb the sugar, more than you would have had you eaten a fruit of the same juice, and spike your blood glucose levels.</p>

<p>Leaving insulin to do its good but also nasty work which I will explain in a future post.</p>

<h1 id="so-what-to-do">So what to do?</h1>

<p>Too much of a good thing is a bad thing.</p>

<p>Even for water which I recommend drinking loads of, drink too much of it, you get Water Toxicity.</p>

<p>I say this focusing on my friend who was drinking fruit juice everyday. Eating anything everyday, especially in large amounts as many fruit juices come in 1 litre bottles, is simply a red flag.</p>

<p>Hence drinking fruit juice is not bad in moderation but it’s something you have to treat as you treat fizzy drinks. I don’t suppose anyone reading this is drinking Coke everyday (and if you are, bless you).</p>

<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>

<p>So no. Fruit juice is not a healthy alternative to Coke and battery acid. Drink fruit juice in the same way you’d want to drink a fizzy drink that you know is spiked with sugars and fructose to make you addicted to it and drink more and more.</p>

<h1 id="bonus-point-aspartame">Bonus point: Aspartame</h1>

<p>A key component of fizzy drinks and fruit juices. It is an artificial sweetener that is <strong>200 times sweeter</strong> than sucrose. Sucrose is what we find in table, white sugar.</p>

<p>During one of my clinical rounds, I heard a doctor say that aspartame has been linked with causing cancer. So naturally I gasped and promised myself to not drink them ever again.</p>

<p>But when I did my own research, I found that there haven’t been any conclusive links of aspartame as a carcinogen. So according to current data, this is false but the world of science isn’t perfect anyway.</p>

<p>This is just another point for drinking more water than anything else.😂</p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Health" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Is it really the healthy alternative that it claims to be?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.postimg.cc/mZ1SRdXz/44d57130-04ae-4135-8e8d-df0b59aef3b1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.postimg.cc/mZ1SRdXz/44d57130-04ae-4135-8e8d-df0b59aef3b1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Your Bacteria and Fibre</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/health/bacteria&fibre" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your Bacteria and Fibre" /><published>2024-01-08T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-01-08T18:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/health/the-bacteria-inside-of-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/health/bacteria&amp;fibre"><![CDATA[<p>We don’t want germs. We domestos them dead. And bacteria is part of what we call germs. But it seems very odd that the same bacteria we kill outside our bodies is also responsible for keeping us well inside.</p>

<p>So let’s start with what they are, what they do, why they are important to us, what we can do to keep them happy (all 38 trillion of them) and as a bonus, highlight the differences between <strong>prebiotic</strong>, <strong>probiotic</strong> and <strong>post-biotics</strong>.</p>

<h1 id="so-whats-the-bacteria-inside-of-you">So what’s the bacteria inside of you?</h1>

<p>Here is the thing. It’s not only bacteria inside your gut. There are</p>

<ul>
  <li>Viruses</li>
  <li>Fungi</li>
  <li>Parasites</li>
  <li>Archae (recently discovered) as well.</li>
</ul>

<p>All these micro-organisms make up your “Gut Microbiome”. Your intestines are a home to an ecosystem to these small organisms and they feed off the food you eat and rely on the warmth on the warmth that your body generates. Quite a smart place to call home.</p>

<h1 id="what-do-they-do">What do they do?</h1>

<p>Humans can’t digest fibre. I am sure you have heard at some point that fibre is good for you but that is weird given that humans can’t naturally digest fibre. But guess who can?</p>

<p>The gut microbes.</p>

<p>The gut bacteria breaks down fibre and releases <em>Short-Chain Fatty Acids (SCFAs)</em>. (They have nothing to do with being fat)  SCFAs are fatty acids with fewer than 6 carbon atoms.</p>

<p>The three most common are <strong>Acetate</strong>, <strong>Propionate</strong> and <strong>Butyrate</strong>.
These SCFAs play crucial roles in the body¹:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Acetate</strong> is important for energy production and synthesis of lipids</li>
  <li><strong>Propionate</strong> is mainly involved in producing glucose in the liver and small intestine</li>
  <li><strong>Butyrate</strong> is the preferred energy source for cells that line the colon.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="why-is-they-are-important">Why is they are important?</h1>

<p>To answer this, I think it’s easier to highlight the bad things that happen if we don’t take care of our gut microbiome.</p>

<p>Your intestines are very selective about what they absorb into the body. There are also some harmful things produced by the gut bacteria such as <strong>bacterial endotoxin</strong> which is not harmful when it’s in the intestines but harmful when it gets into the blood.</p>

<p>Butyrate as mentioned above, is the preferred energy source for cells that line the colon. Butyrate is formed from fibre that you eat. It follows that if you eat less fibre, you are eating less of what your intestinal lining needs to stay closed and not feeding the bacteria that form butyrate.</p>

<p>What this leads to is inflammation of the intestinal lining and entrance of bacterial endotoxin into your blood. Leading to inflammation is all of the wrong places in your body.</p>

<p>In addition to that, inflammation in your intestines may lead to colon cancer and other nasty health complications.</p>

<h1 id="how-to-keep-our-gut-microbiome-happy">How to keep our Gut Microbiome happy</h1>

<p>Fibre.</p>

<p>That’s it.</p>

<p>Foods that have fibre are plant based. That is</p>

<ul>
  <li>Fruits</li>
  <li>Legumes</li>
  <li>Vegetables</li>
  <li>Seeds &amp; Nuts</li>
</ul>

<p>I do realise however, that this is largely the Zimbabwean diet. From sugar beans to nuts. So I suppose that much of the nation is okay in terms of the gut microbiome. But it’s this second part that is more important.</p>

<h2 id="foods-that-affect-the-gut-microbiome">Foods that affect the gut microbiome</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Artificial sweeteners.
  Those found in “diet-drinks” and other similar foods.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Processed/Refined foods.
  These deserve an article on their own. But they are more damaging than nutritive to the body and the gut microbiome is not spared.</li>
  <li>Red meat.
  Seems like beef isn’t responsible for gout only but can also affect your heart and gut.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="prebiotics-vs-probiotics-vs-postbiotics">Prebiotics Vs Probiotics Vs Postbiotics</h1>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Prebiotics</strong> are plant fibers found primarily in foods that contain complex carbohydrates, like resistant starch and fiber. They act as food for bacteria, promoting their growth and health. Foods rich in prebiotics include whole wheat, bananas, soybeans, and greens. Essentially plants</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Probiotics</strong> are live bacteria and yeast contained in cultured foods. They promote healthy digestive function, support immune health, and influence overall wellness. Probiotic-rich foods include yogurt and kombucha.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Postbiotics</strong> are byproducts of the good bacteria left behind when probiotics ferment prebiotics. They contain dead bacteria, short-chain fatty acids, and peptides that support bodily function</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>

<p>This was not at all exhaustive on the topic of gut microbiota. But I believe that if you were at zero, you now know to spare a thought for the 38 trillion strong army inside your gut.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Health" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore the world of gut microbes with me plus why fibre is very important! Learn about these tiny organisms in our digestive system and their impact on our health.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.postimg.cc/RZbK4bpk/63d82727-dfbd-4f5c-9a6c-8c127ecc231a.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.postimg.cc/RZbK4bpk/63d82727-dfbd-4f5c-9a6c-8c127ecc231a.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>