<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-05T17:42:29+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tanaka Mawere</title><subtitle>Incompetent C# Programmer and Keyboardist + Bassist from Harare. Currently an unfortunate medical student at UZ and pretends to exercise at times.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Now a week off YouTube…</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/battle%20with%20social%20media/youtube/productivity/2023/12/05/a-week-off-youtube.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Now a week off YouTube…" /><published>2023-12-05T17:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-12-05T17:30:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/battle%20with%20social%20media/youtube/productivity/2023/12/05/a-week-off-youtube</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/battle%20with%20social%20media/youtube/productivity/2023/12/05/a-week-off-youtube.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="going-against-habit">Going against habit</h1>

<p>A week doesn’t seem like a long time but considering that a day wouldn’t pass without me typing “you…” and having the browser auto-predict that I want to open the land of milk and time-wasting that is YouTube, it really is something! Something that wasn’t easy at all.</p>

<h3 id="friday">Friday</h3>

<p>All the other days of the week, I was definitely fine. Until Friday.</p>

<p>And this is because usually on Friday afternoons, I open up my YouTube and watch videos till the evening. (Yes, my Friday afternoons are quite drab. It’s not a competition). So on the Friday I didn’t have YouTube, I really felt it. It being withdrawal symptoms.</p>

<p>Now, I don’t know the intensity of withdrawal symptoms that people who have had a drug addiction go through but I am sure they are almost the same as what I felt on Friday.</p>

<p>I felt a sense of something missing, a longing for YouTube, to just open it. I didn’t have an idea of what I wanted to watch. I just wanted it there.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It is in the moment that I realised that yes, YouTube (and social media) really is addictive.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But I distracted myself by relying on my other nemesis…</p>

<h1 id="whatsapp">WhatsApp</h1>

<p>Yes, I haven’t watched YouTube in a week but my usage of WhatsApp shot up. Not dramatically but significantly, especially for someone who already thought I spend more time than is necessary on Zuck’s messaging app.</p>

<p>I was really conscious about simply replacing the YouTube addiction and misuse with misusing WhatsApp which is my other enemy and I sort of failed in that.</p>

<p>Of course, it’s not a 1 to 1 match for the time you will spend. For example, WhatsApp, once you are not in conversation with no one, you can easily close the app unlike YouTube which presents to you more eye candy in the form of attracting thumbnails and videos once you refresh the page.</p>

<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>

<p>I have been more productive in a way. Finally began to make progress on a project of mine and started being a bit more intentional, but I am definitely not where I want to be.</p>

<p>As for WhatsApp, it’s another battle that I have commenced. I am experimenting with a few things to see healthy ways to still have WhatsApp in my life. I will probably have to outline why WhatsApp is a problem to me because I have just realised that some people might not understand why I don’t like WhatsApp so much.</p>

<p>Onwards I guess…</p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Battle with Social Media" /><category term="YouTube" /><category term="Productivity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I last watched a YouTube video a week ago and man, has it been something]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.postimg.cc/mrw8Gp9t/9d897122-329a-4818-abf6-e340d63a3769.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.postimg.cc/mrw8Gp9t/9d897122-329a-4818-abf6-e340d63a3769.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">I quit social media and got addicted to YouTube</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/battle%20with%20social%20media/youtube/productivity/2023/11/27/quit-social-media-addicted-to-youtube.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I quit social media and got addicted to YouTube" /><published>2023-11-27T16:53:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-11-27T16:53:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/battle%20with%20social%20media/youtube/productivity/2023/11/27/quit-social-media-addicted-to-youtube</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/battle%20with%20social%20media/youtube/productivity/2023/11/27/quit-social-media-addicted-to-youtube.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-story">The Story</h1>

<p>I left social media, or at least a part of it, in 2021 completely. Reasons are for another article.</p>

<p>My Facebook account that I had opened in 2009 was deleted. The Instagram account that I had built quite a following on same thing. Twitter? Got the axe as well. I remember also having SnapChat and deleting it a week later too.</p>

<p>Overall, what was left was WhatsApp and YouTube. And these two were easy to excuse.</p>

<ul>
  <li>WhatsApp =&gt; My school sends updates through groups so I can’t possibly remove it?</li>
  <li>YouTube =&gt; I watch educational content only such as videos on coding or fixing stuff. In any case, with the time I am using on YouTube I am still being productive.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="the-problem">The Problem</h1>

<p>The problem however is that I have long believed that since I deleted social media (Instagram, Twitter, Facebook; the classics), I had more time to be productive. And by productivity, I mean actually study more or do the things that I really want to do.</p>

<p>But on closer inspection, I am no different to someone who has 10 social media apps on their phone and changes between each app. I really just replaced the time I thought I was saving with spending it on WhatsApp and YouTube, all because they are both easy to excuse as not wasteful.</p>

<h1 id="focusing-on-youtube">Focusing on YouTube</h1>

<p>I will tackle WhatsApp later. YouTube is really what forced me to think about this and write it down.</p>

<p>I take pride in that I never got onto the TikTok, Reels or Shorts train. Because short videos take advantage of our short attention spans and make them even shorter. So I always watch long form content on YouTube, usually videos lasting 9 minutes or more. And because most of the videos I watch are educational, I am able to <em>rationally</em> justify spending 2 hours watching video after video after video.</p>

<p>But truth be told, I have a growing discontent internally for the following reasons</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Time wasting
 When you have something hard to do, it’s very easy to open a browser, type “you..” and let auto-predict direct you on your way to watching videos. And the YouTube algorithm is so good that it’ll recommend video after video after video, and in no time, you have spent 3 hours on the site.</p>

    <p>This in particular hurts studying time and time meant to be working on projects that actually matter in the real world…</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Motivation depletion
 I haven’t looked for studies to back this up hence all this is personal experience. 
 I have noticed that stopping to watch YouTube while stuck in a YouTube rabbit hole is hard. Extremely hard. You get into a state of being tranced into waiting for the next video to give you a dopamine hit. 
 And even when you manage to snap out of it, you don’t feel particularly excited or motivated to be productive. You are just there, feeling like a wasteman.</p>

    <p>I really don’t know what it is about social media that after using it, you feel sort of depleted and tired. And YouTube was doing that to me.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Asking myself what I just watched</p>

    <p>I got into an exercise of asking myself the importance and relevance of what I just watched to my life. Okay, I now know what “Clean Architecture” is but where does that apply to me? It is educational, but relevance is zero.</p>

    <p>The times I really like is when I end up watching a Beta Squad video. Now let me take the time to say this PSA</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>If you don’t know what the Beta Squad is, I envy your life and the focus you have in it. Keep it going.</p>
    </blockquote>

    <p>Anyway, I don’t know what relevance or particular importance it is to me to see Chunkz guess African’s ethnicity based on their language. So why should I watch it? Thing is I don’t do it willingly. I end up <em>there</em>. And that’s just an effect of being tranced into a social media consumption rabbit hole.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h1 id="seeing-it-for-what-it-is">Seeing it for what it is</h1>

<p>Given the reasons above and how negatively YouTube is beginning to impact my life, I had to call a duck, a duck because it was quacking like a duck. YouTube is making me not focus on the things I want to achieve, it’s wasting time, makes me feel like a wasteman, gets me stuck in 2 hours watching cycles and more importantly, it’s really hacked my dopamine system.</p>

<p>And even the times I justified YouTube as being productive, is it really? And asking myself that question led me to thinking and believing that I left social media, only to get addicted to YouTube, which is a form of social media in itself.</p>

<h1 id="the-plan-now">The plan now</h1>

<p>Going cold turkey on YouTube until 5 April. (Close to my birthday)</p>

<p>Typing this, I feel unsure I can accomplish this since YouTube is a mainstay of my daily living. But it’s a necessary challenge in which I will question if YouTube really is that important and try to prove to myself that I can live without it.</p>

<p>I am going to be very very bored hence I will end up writing more nonsense like this on my website to not make me go crazy. By the way, if you got this far in the article, could you kindly send a ‘😝’ emoji <a href="https://wa.me/263785468923">to my WhatsApp</a>. I’d appreciate it.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Next up on the chopping block? WhatsApp. <em>Coming for you Zuck!</em></p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Battle with Social Media" /><category term="YouTube" /><category term="Productivity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The digital definition of evading a pothole and driving straight into a pit.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.postimg.cc/c4Rwg4Lx/quit-social-media.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.postimg.cc/c4Rwg4Lx/quit-social-media.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t tell, cause thought</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/productivity/2023/11/24/dont-tell-cause-thought.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don’t tell, cause thought" /><published>2023-11-24T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-11-24T18:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thoughts/productivity/2023/11/24/dont-tell-cause-thought</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/productivity/2023/11/24/dont-tell-cause-thought.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="a-story">A story</h1>

<p>A few weeks ago, my school group (8 of us) had patient case presentations. It was a Friday and given the vibe of the day of ‘I want to get this over with so that I go back home and vegetate on some TikTok’, each of us wanted to go present first and leave the hospital. No one wanted to go last so in my head, I had no problem with being the ‘sacrificial lamb’ that waits. I had no problem with it until someone said, “you should go last because you usually have no problem with it.”</p>

<p>I don’t know what it was but it felt like a switch was flipped in my head to just be antagonistic. It was saying “I was okay with going last on my own volition but since you said I should, I don’t want to anymore.”</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I am sure we all relate to how you could wake up one morning, feel like you could do the dishes, sweep the floors and even mop the ceiling. UNTIL, until your mom tells you to do so.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s like all the internal motivation you had to do something just vanishes out the window and you get into a “I don’t want to do it anymore” type of mode.</p>

<h3 id="we-are-all-rebels">We are all rebels</h3>

<p>There is a certain part in us all that just doesn’t want to be told what to do. Certainly in me, being hard and strong headed is a trait. So knowing this about humans, what do you do when you want to communicate with your peers effectively or write something?</p>

<h1 id="dont-tell-cause-thought">Don’t tell, cause thought</h1>

<p>I was really trying to think of a catch statement do distill all this. “Don’t tell, cause thought” sounds grammaticaly correct but I am not settled with it😂. But it will have to make do. And it’s really self-explanatory.</p>

<p>Don’t tell people what to do. We don’t want to be told what to do. Instead, lead people to think for themselves. No wonder there is the over-reliance on the not-so-common ‘common sense.’ We expect individuals to get to certain conclusions using ‘common sense’ (but of course it’s not so common) and that’s how people want to be treated.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>People love freedom and autonomy. The best feeling is doing something because you did it because <em>you wanted to</em>. Not because you were told to.</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>

<p>Hence as a communicator, speaker or ‘content creator👀’, aim to present the facts in a way that enables people to get to their own conclusions. Cross your fingers that <em>if whatever you are saying makes sense</em>, people are also going to get to the same conclusion as well.</p>

<p>And if they feel like they are forming their own opinion or conclusions without you being instructive or pushy, it’s much more likely to see people respond positively to you.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><category term="Productivity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[People don't listen when you tell them something. Simple fact of life, so don't tell them. Make them think.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1495293453185-532fbd0a872c?w=500&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;q=60&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=M3wxMjA3fDB8MHxzZWFyY2h8NHx8cXVpZXR8ZW58MHx8MHx8fDA%3D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1495293453185-532fbd0a872c?w=500&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;q=60&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=M3wxMjA3fDB8MHxzZWFyY2h8NHx8cXVpZXR8ZW58MHx8MHx8fDA%3D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Defeating WhatsApp</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/development/programming/2023/11/18/defeating-whatsapp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Defeating WhatsApp" /><published>2023-11-18T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-11-18T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thoughts/development/programming/2023/11/18/defeating-whatsapp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/development/programming/2023/11/18/defeating-whatsapp.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="ma-runner">ma-runner</h1>

<p>I recently went into a shop that sells good quality clothes. Thing is I don’t go for shopping. I will go 5 years without buying a clothing item just because I don’t like going shop by shop looking for clothes.</p>

<p>Then it hit me.</p>

<p>Why not make an app for this? For lazy people like me to do their clothes shopping online?</p>

<p>Then it hit me again.</p>

<p>My girlfriend’s WhatsApp has close to 30 groups of people who sell clothes in there (I don’t like them because they might hide a chat from a blesser or someone she’s cheating with when I am doing my daily check ups on her phone.) Add to that, the use of Facebook Marketplace.</p>

<p>And just like that, the Zimbabwean Amazon died before it went anywhere.</p>

<h1 id="its-everywhere">It’s everywhere</h1>

<p>And if you think about it, there are WhatsApp groups for everything, not just clothes. Food, cars, books, movies (ehm ehm). In first world countries, there are separate apps for each category.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Just for food in first world countries, Chicken Inn, Nandos and kwaMereki would have their own separate food ordering apps. No wonder there are more jobs there than here.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Everything is in WhatsApp. So as a developer trying to remove people from WhatsApp, natural question to ask is “why?” Why is everything aggregated in WhatsApp groups?</p>

<h1 id="to-state-the-obvious">To state the obvious…</h1>

<p>It’s convenient. Simply that. I already have a WhatsApp bundle to stalk my relative’s status updates who recently left Zimbabwe and isn’t sending money back home but is going on holidays to what’s it called, Bhali, Balie? So why not just look for clothes in the same app by just joining groups?</p>

<h1 id="data-is-expensive">Data is expensive?</h1>

<p>A few years ago, you would have convinced me that it was because data is expensive and people just buy WhatsApp bundles. Which is still true to some extent. It’s more likely for someone to have a WhatsApp bundle and not a data bundle in Zimbabwe. But I don’t buy this reason completely.</p>

<p>The number of people now using Instagram and more ubiquitously, TikTok, makes me think that of course, not everyone has money for data bundles, but if someone is using their data for TikTok, they have probably 5mb to spare for using a different app.</p>

<p>Granted the number of people who use TikTok in Zimbabwe, is still low compared to the total population but I suppose with time, they will increase. Which lead me to…</p>

<h1 id="time">Time</h1>

<p>I don’t know what the solution is for developers to pull the population away from WhatsApp to their apps but something tells me that with time and as more and more people are digitally connected in Zimbabwe, this is likely to change. Because for all their merit, WhatsApp groups are limited.</p>

<p>There is a lot of spam eating into your device memory. You can’t really search for a product and of course, payment systems. It’s a hassle that I suppose people in Zimbabwe in a few years will be ready to eliminate.</p>

<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>

<p>But what do you think? Are there any actionable steps to pull people away from WhatsApp groups towards using dedicated apps or websites? Because WhatsApp really is a developer’s enemy and developers need to fight against it.</p>

<p><em>P.S: I do not have a girlfriend. Neither would I do daily checkups on her phone. I hope…</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><category term="Development" /><category term="Programming" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A programmer in Zimbabwe's greatest enemy is WhatsApp. How do we defeat it? I have no idea]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1632435499152-18838be77960?w=500&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;q=60&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=M3wxMjA3fDB8MHxzZWFyY2h8MTB8fHdoYXRzYXBwfGVufDB8fDB8fHww" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1632435499152-18838be77960?w=500&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;q=60&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=M3wxMjA3fDB8MHxzZWFyY2h8MTB8fHdoYXRzYXBwfGVufDB8fDB8fHww" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Catch of Forex Trading…</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-catch-of-forex-trading" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Catch of Forex Trading…" /><published>2023-11-15T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-11-15T18:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the-catch-of-forex-trading</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-catch-of-forex-trading"><![CDATA[<h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1>

<p>The number of times I have cast my privacy-disrespecting eye over to someone’s phone (most often a dude) and he passes through his apps screen, chances are I see Metatrader 4 and/or 5. And if you don’t know Metatrader 4 or 5, you are either a girl or a pocketically-blessed dude.</p>

<p>The subject matter I want to talk about doesn’t need you to have any forex trading knowledge because I will keep it as generic as possible. So let’s dive into the catch of forex trading.</p>

<h1 id="an-egg">An egg…</h1>

<p>Ever heard the statement that the hardest thing to cook is an egg? And it’s because so easy to cook. Doesn’t make sense right?</p>

<p>We are used to eating eggs that are either overcooked or overcooked-er. They are always way to crispy on the outside if they are fried, some to the point of qualifying as biltong. Worse even, try making a sunny side up egg without browning the edges. What about boiling an egg without making the york into a rubbery, minature ‘zadza-dama’? I won’t even mention poaching.</p>

<p>The point of the overly-drawn joke above is that making a perfect egg is hard because the way to make an edible egg is easy to understand and do. It’s just frying in oil, boiling in water etc. That’s simple. The barriers to making an egg are so low and that’s what makes it hard. Contrast that with making a <em>insert some complicated recipe I will search on Google that only Gordon Ramsey can make</em>. The fact that you need the skills of Gordon Ramsey to make it stops you from even daring to make it.</p>

<h1 id="so-what">So what?</h1>

<blockquote>
  <p>Forex trading is like making an egg.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s so easy to put in $10 to start trading with. All you need is to make a broker account, download Metatrader and start getting your losses because you probably have no idea what you are doing. The barriers of entry into forex trading are extremely low hence anyone can sign up to do it.</p>

<p>Much like making a perfect egg, the average Joe who has entered into forex trading will fail. And does fail. No wonder you hear so many people saying “forex trading is a scam” or something to that effect.</p>

<p>And I don’t blame people for signing up to trade. All the other potential <del>legal</del> ways of making money either need some skill, quite a bit of capital and more effort than that which is required in forex trading. 
But that ease of entry into trading is also the downfall for many and it is the catch.</p>

<h1 id="the-effects-of-the-catch">The effects of the catch</h1>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Trading, like any other business, needs capital. - More likely than not, if you deposit any amount below $100, you are going to lose it because when trades are still in red, your capital can’t handle it. And for you to make sensible money from such a low amount, you’d have to over-leverage your small capital (essentially trading more than you can). So in the end, you’d be at a disadvantage.</p>

    <p>I never understood it while starting out while some brokers said their minimum deposit amount was $500. But now that I have gained the experience I have, anything below $100, you are probably going to lose it. This is another blog post on it’s own explaining this more.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>There is no selection criteria - You just can’t be a doctor. There are many exams over the 5+ years of training that make sure you are up to scratch with your skills and knowledge to treat patients.</p>

    <p>Not with trading though.</p>

    <p>The only person stopping you from risking all you own is you. No one evaluates your skills and knowledge about trading or the market prior to trading except you. Hence anyone who wants to trade, can. And that is ultimately bad for them as they will end up blaming the markets for their lack of experience when they lose everything.</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>Side note though. People go get degrees so that they trade for big banks and sometimes fail to make profits even with tens of millions of dollars to trade with. What makes us think that watching YouTube videos for a weekend and armed with $10 of capital, we are going to buy a Ferrari and lift the whole family out of poverty?</p>
    </blockquote>
  </li>
</ol>

<h1 id="the-take-aways">The take-aways</h1>

<p>I wish all brokers had $500 as their minimum trading amount. I was angry about it when I started learning how to trade but it helped me not lose more than I did as I was learning. And it’s only from losing money that I learnt this lesson, hard. If someone asks me for advice on trading, I immediately tell them that if they don’t have $500 or more to trade, leave it alone.</p>

<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>

<p>While I understand that trading might seems like a low-cost option of a side hustle, because it’s so easy to get into now, that should not be mistaken for ease of execution. Starting to forex trade is easy. Forexing <em>trading</em> itself, a totally different beast on its own.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Don’t be fooled by how easy it is to start trading. And that is the catch of forex trading.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Forex" /><category term="Thoughts" /><category term="Trading" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This year marks 3 years since I started learning how to trade... Here's something I learnt]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1569025743873-ea3a9ade89f9?w=500&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;q=60&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=M3wxMjA3fDB8MHxzZWFyY2h8Nnx8Zm9yZXglMjB0cmFkaW5nfGVufDB8fDB8fHww" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1569025743873-ea3a9ade89f9?w=500&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;q=60&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=M3wxMjA3fDB8MHxzZWFyY2h8Nnx8Zm9yZXglMjB0cmFkaW5nfGVufDB8fDB8fHww" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Put your eggs in one basket</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2023/11/07/put-your-eggs-in-one-basket.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Put your eggs in one basket" /><published>2023-11-07T12:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-11-07T12:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2023/11/07/put-your-eggs-in-one-basket</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2023/11/07/put-your-eggs-in-one-basket.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1>

<p>I am currently reading Stephen Bartlett’s “Diary of a CEO: 33 laws of something (I have forgotten and lazy to check it up)” and there is a chapter that says Plan B is bad for Plan A.</p>

<p>That whole chapter resonated with me. Imagine you were living in a shack and you had one opportunity to free yourself and your family from poverty. You’d work hard to make that opportunity worthwhile and if you don’t succeed as much, you will be close to some definition of success. However, if you have an alternative path to follow, you won’t work as hard on Plan A because Plan B is a safety net for. Hence the commitment, the almost deluded belief in Plan A will not be there as you have comfort of having another way to go.</p>

<p>Hence you won’t execute plan A well or fail miserably at it.</p>

<h1 id="my-story">My Story</h1>

<p>I have seen this in myself. My plan A is to make something with my coding skills and have that sustain me. My plan B is doing this medicine thingy. But because medicine is a safe bet and comforting, I am putting nowhere enough effort in plan A that would make me succeed at the very least. I suppose that if I wasn’t enrolled into medical school and sitting at home (of course not with African parents), plan A would probably be all there is and I would put all my being and effort into it.</p>

<p>But because plan B exists, I am calm when I am not supposed to be.</p>

<h1 id="this-is-zimbabwe">This is Zimbabwe</h1>

<blockquote>
  <p>But that is the Zimbabwean story isn’t it? One thing can’t sustain you. You have to have a job, a side hustle, a farm and three Visa applications to go to the UK, Australia and/or Poland (in that order) to help old white people bath.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So realistically speaking, it’s not bad for plan B to exist. In Zimbabwe, it’s a necessity even. But there is a need to be conscious of your priorities and what you want to achieve most so that side-plans do not derail the first one.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Having a 'Plan B' is bad for 'Plan A']]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1498654077810-12c21d4d6dc3?q=80&amp;w=2070&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=M3wxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8fA%3D%3D" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1498654077810-12c21d4d6dc3?q=80&amp;w=2070&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=M3wxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8fA%3D%3D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">My current experience with impostor syndrome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2023/11/03/impostor-syndrome.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My current experience with impostor syndrome" /><published>2023-11-03T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-11-03T18:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2023/11/03/impostor-syndrome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2023/11/03/impostor-syndrome.html"><![CDATA[<p>I suppose being a late teenager and getting into your twenties, you go into life with so many ideas of how things are supposed to go, how things are etc. After all, your life before university is almost as black and white, wrong and right as it can get. You are either a good student or a bad student, you are either a good child or a bad child, you are either a good friend or a bad friend. You get the idea. But then you get to experience life in its whole, I believe in university. You start to appreciate that life is not black and white but many many shades of grey.</p>

<p>That’s what happened to me this year. I was never scared to share information with people. I’d read dozens of books a year, listen to many podcasts and read many articles on how to be the best person I could be (I still do). I would then share this information. That was one of my motivations to start this blog, to have a place to share things I found interesting with people around me, hoping it’d help.</p>

<p>However, events that have happened this year, many that I caused to myself, have led me to question myself more. And it has led me to question <a href="https://tanakamawere.co.zw/thoughts/2023/10/29/by-whose-authority">who am I to say anything that I say?</a> I suppose this is still me reeling from the events of this year and I will eventually get back to feeling like myself and writing regardless.</p>

<h2 id="it-really-doesnt-matter">It really doesn’t matter</h2>

<p>I have had plans to start a podcast for at least a year now and I will. I wanted to start it as a podcast to give advice and lessons that I have learnt from my very short life, especially to young, Christian boys. But again, the question springs up. Who am I to do that? The point of the podcast has now changed then. Instead of me giving advice (which I don’t have anyway), let me talk to people who are way ahead of me. Doctors, parents, pastors etc, people who obviously know something about life because I know nothing.</p>

<p>In summary, it’ll be a podcast where I selfishly talk to people who are way ahead of me in life and ask them questions that I have. I’ll be learning and hopefully, you’ll be learning too.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>I wrote this today so that I am keep a public record of me going through impostor syndrome for the first time in my life and seeing how I will overcome it. Typing this, I am now questioning if ‘impostor syndrome’ is a problem anyway.😂 Maybe it’s a way for people to know their places in life.</p>

<p>But I will go back to my past cadence of posting things I would have found interesting. That shouldn’t cause any problems since the information wouldn’t be coming from me directly😂. And when the podcast comes around, it’ll be even better.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Key takeaway for me: I am not old enough to be giving ‘life advice’. Don’t I ever will or dare to.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A bit more quiet and shush from me...]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.postimg.cc/8zpTck2s/impostor.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.postimg.cc/8zpTck2s/impostor.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Are Minister Mahendere’s lyrics biblical?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/faith/2023/10/31/tangai-neni-lyrics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are Minister Mahendere’s lyrics biblical?" /><published>2023-10-31T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-31T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/faith/2023/10/31/tangai-neni-lyrics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/faith/2023/10/31/tangai-neni-lyrics.html"><![CDATA[<p>It was late at night, at a time I know I should be asleep. It’s as easy as going offline, closing my eyes and going to sleep. But of course, I don’t do that. Instead, in a conversation with my friend, (who was honestly sleepy to the point of just indulging me by replying so ‘conversation’ might be some sort of a stretch), I got to wonder, <em>are Minister Mahendere’s lyrics to ‘Tangai Neni’ biblical?</em></p>

<h2 id="disclaimers">Disclaimers</h2>

<p>Before I go on, I should state a few things.</p>
<ol>
  <li>If you are a Minister Mahendere fan, please (and pretty please) do not take this as an attack. You will see that in this article, I won’t even claim whether it’s wrong (maybe once I get more information, I will have a solid opinion). I am simply in a quest for truth.</li>
  <li>I am not the biggest fan of his in any case. It’s not that I don’t like his music and him, I just don’t listen to his music. I have nothing against him. (I felt I had to say this to remove any bias that might be perceived in this article).</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="things-i-have-questions-about">Things I have questions about</h2>

<p>I am going to try to pose questions that I have about the song. I will try to be as objective as possible and keep them as questions. Please do feel free to reply with answers and I will update this article accordingly.</p>

<p>Now that that is out of the way…</p>

<h3 id="tangai-neni">Tangai neni</h3>

<p>What does that mean? It’s implication is that we are in a competition to be blessed so “might as well start here Lord”.</p>

<p>In addition to that, an obvious question is “Is this a song about God or about me?”</p>

<p>The whole song’s lyrics are “Tangai neni”, “Mugopedza neni”, “Ndioneiwo”… Matthew 6 vs 33 says “But seek first His kingdom and His righteousness, and all these things will be given to you as well.”</p>

<p>Are we not in direct violation of that when we ask God to do something for us first? And I say for us <em>first</em> because God is considered at the end, sort of as an afterthought with the following lyrics, at the end of the song…</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>I will testify
I will testify
Of Your goodness
Of Your mercy
</code></pre></div></div>

<h3 id="prosperity-gospel-repackaged">Prosperity gospel repackaged?</h3>

<p>There is a part of the song that goes like</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Ko paye
Pamuno promoter vanhu venyu
Imbo tangai neni Ishe
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Another</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Pamunokomborera vana venyu
Imbo tangai neni Ishe
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>There is a very materialistic feel to the song. Prosperity gospel-like. And who can blame him? It sells easily. No wonder the song has 2.7 million views on YouTube. But then again, is it biblical?</p>

<h3 id="so-for-those-who-things-dont-work-out">So for those who things don’t work out…</h3>

<p>There are lyrics saying</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Mwari
Iko kutenda ndinako
Kushoko renyu
Saka ndioneiwo Mwari
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>This is one of the reasons why people end up leaving the church. “Ah it didn’t work out? You didn’t have enough faith. Keep pushing” without stopping to ask, “Is this what God wants for me? What actually is God’s will?”</p>

<p>Romans 9 vs 21 says “Does not the potter have the right to make out of the same lump of clay some pottery for special purposes and some for common use?” God is sovereign and His will <em>will</em> be done.</p>

<p>Is it not better that we first ask God what His will is and then pray for it to be done instead of encouraging people to have faith in whatever, no matter the reason?”</p>

<h2 id="in-conclusion">In conclusion</h2>

<p>If it wasn’t clear, my biggest problem with the song is that it seems to be about me and not about God. It seems to be about what I want and not what God wants. Further to that, it seems to be encouraging an ATM type of God. “Lord I want to make the first withdrawal so tangai neni”.</p>

<p>Is that really what the New Testament is encouraging our relationship with God to be like?</p>

<p>Again, please do feel free to reply me on my <a href="https://wa.me/263785468923">WhatsApp by clicking right here</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Faith" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Minister Mahendere's popular song "Tangai Neni" came into question yesterday and I fell down a rabbit hole. Are they biblical?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/zKL7xVbXSpI/sddefault.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/zKL7xVbXSpI/sddefault.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A theory about that gut feeling</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2023/10/30/a-theory-about-that-gut-feeling.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A theory about that gut feeling" /><published>2023-10-30T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-30T18:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2023/10/30/a-theory-about-that-gut-feeling</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2023/10/30/a-theory-about-that-gut-feeling.html"><![CDATA[<p>My friend and I, we take long walks after Sunday church so that we avoid having to cook and do chores at home after service. 
During one of these walks, we talked about what ‘gut feeling’ is.</p>

<p>I know we have all had it at some point. You consciously get to a conclusion about something but something just doesn’t ‘feel’ right. And because it’s ‘feeling’ based, many people tend to dismiss it because of social constructs that feelings are unimportant. But we rationalised it in another way.</p>

<h2 id="our-theory-on-gut-feelings">Our Theory On Gut Feelings</h2>

<p>We are consciously prone to deceiving ourselves. We disregard things consciously things when they don’t fit the model of what we want things to be. I might know that I don’t have a lot of money for fuel while deciding to buy a car but will gladly disregard that when I see a Benz in my price range. (Obviously the engine is missing and it has banana peels for brakes if it is that cheap.)</p>

<p>Therefore</p>

<p><strong>If we are so prone to lying to ourselves, <em>what if</em> the gut feeling is the conclusion that your subconscious mind has gotten to without lying to itself?</strong></p>

<p>Your subconscious mind is probably the truest you and acts as a repository of your values and principles. So it doesn’t seem unlikely, to me at least, that the subconscious mind will make the best decision for you (without you being aware of it - that’s the subconscious mind) but just present it as a ‘gut feeling’. This probably happens while you are still trying to rationalise consciously you eating that cake in the fridge at 11pm.</p>

<p>And another funny thing too. Your ‘gut’ is always right. This is from anecdotal evidence of course, but I am sure some of you might relate to this.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Whatever your gut was feeling iffy about, in the future, you probably realise it was trying to tell you something and it was right.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="why-is-it-a-gut-feeling">Why is it a ‘gut feeling’?</h2>

<p>Scientists have attempted to explain why you feel it in your gut or stomach. Along the whole lining of your digestive tract, there is a complex system of nerves called the ‘Enteric Nervous System’. Now, there is no conclusive evidence that there is a link between this nervous system and ‘feeling it in your gut’ (maybe you just ate a lot).</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>It’s just a theory but a theory that makes sense to me. It helps so that I don’t dismiss the feelings I have about something. It’s probably right and I am the one lying to myself.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Do I need to rationalise everything and understand how I got to every conclusion I have? Probably not. Here's why.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1636082106091-493a3696eaf4?auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;q=60&amp;w=500&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=M3wxMjA3fDB8MHxzZWFyY2h8MTB8fGluc3RpbmN0fGVufDB8fDB8fHww" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1636082106091-493a3696eaf4?auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;q=60&amp;w=500&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=M3wxMjA3fDB8MHxzZWFyY2h8MTB8fGluc3RpbmN0fGVufDB8fDB8fHww" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">By whose authority do I write?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2023/10/29/by-whose-authority.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="By whose authority do I write?" /><published>2023-10-29T06:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-29T06:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2023/10/29/by-whose-authority</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2023/10/29/by-whose-authority.html"><![CDATA[<p>Whenever I write something that I want to post here later, I find myself cringing sometimes. The question in my head will be</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Who are you to write about this?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Which is a good question which I answer in the following ways.</p>

<h1 id="1-i-am-no-one-really">1. I am no one really.</h1>

<p>I write and post primarily for myself and to organise my thoughts more. The feeling of having to go public with what you are thinking forces you to think the thoughts more thoroughly.</p>

<p>That’s the whole value of putting things in public such as this. Richard Feynman’s claim to fame is that he popularised the notion that if you can’t teach something, you probably don’t understand it. Posting thoughts in public isn’t necessarily teaching but the action of posting itself is an exercise in helping you understand what you are posting.</p>

<p>This is the first selfish reason</p>

<h1 id="2-let-the-information-out-there">2. Let the information out there</h1>

<p>The other reason is that at this very young, juvenile age, I don’t know a lot. But I might be one step ahead in a journey that someone else younger is on. So what I share and experience might help in some way. Very unlikely but I hope so.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tanaka Mawere</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A bit of an imposter syndrome piece]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1455390582262-044cdead277a?ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=M3wxMjA3fDB8MHxzZWFyY2h8Mnx8d3JpdGluZ3xlbnwwfHwwfHx8MA%3D%3D&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=500&amp;q=60" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1455390582262-044cdead277a?ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=M3wxMjA3fDB8MHxzZWFyY2h8Mnx8d3JpdGluZ3xlbnwwfHwwfHx8MA%3D%3D&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=500&amp;q=60" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>